So top of ל"ח ע"א Lamed Chet Amud Aleph we pick up
with the
following. ספק ויבם, Safek Veyavam, it is six lines from the top,
seven lines, one, two, three, four, six or seven lines. Seven lines
from the top. ספק ויבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי סבא. Safek Veyavam Sheba'u
Lachlok Bi-Nichsei Sabba. Now
גרשון Gershon here and the brother-in-law שמעון Shimon are coming to argue
over who gets the inheritance of יעקב. Yaakov.
Here
is יעקב. Yaakov.
And he has got his field. Now גרשון Gershon wants to claim
that he is what in this role? Whose son? Who is he?
ראובן. Reuven. Then he gets half of that field.
שמעון Shimon basically says, now שמעון Shimon is still alive, שמעון Shimon
basically says you are my son, you ain't getting anything until I
die and I get the whole field. ספק ויבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי
סבא. Safek Veyavam Sheba'u Lachlok Bi-Nichsei Sabba. ספק אמר האי גברא בר
מיתנא הוא. Safek Amar Hai Gavra Bar Mitna Hu. I am the
son of the dead person. Funny he talks about himself in the
third person. Anyway, that person is the son, meaning I am the
son of ראובן. Reuven. ופלגא דידי הוא U-Palga Didi Hu and I
get half the field. יבם אמר Yavam Amar and יבם Yavam says,
את ברא דידי את, At Bera Didi At, you are my son,
ולא שייך לך ולא מידי V-Lo Shayecha Lach V-Lo Midi and you
don't have any part of that field.
And if you keep on making problems I am going to write
you out of my will.
הוי יבם ודאי וספק ספק ואין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. Havei Yavam
Vadai V-Safek Safek V-Ein Safek Motzi Mi-Yedei Vadai. So the גמרא Gemara
says here, he has got a claim to the whole field in
a definite capacity. He knows what capacity he has got, he has
got a claim to the whole field. He has a questionable claim,
right, because he made, you know, he definitely knows that even if
גרשון Gershon is ראובן's Reuven son, right, then שמעון Shimon is still
getting half the field, correct? Everybody got that? Even if... so שמעון
Shimon says, look, I have a definite claim. I am a definite
heir to this field, either half or whole.
גרשון Gershon basically is I am possibly an heir to this field.
I mean he says it as a ודאי, Vadai, but the reality
is he is possibly an heir. So he is a definite heir,
he is a possible heir, so get out of here גרשון, Gershon,
we give it to the definite heir and המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
Ha-Motzi Me-Chaveiro Alav Ha-Re'aya. So שמעון Shimon gets it all.
ספק ובני יבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי סבא. Safek U-Vnei Yavam Sheba'u Lachlok
Bi-Nichsei Sabba. Now שמעון Shimon is dead. So now גרשון Gershon is
arguing with קהת Kehat and מררי Merari over יעקב's Yaakov field.
גרשון Gershon still wants to say
he
is ראובן's Reuven son
and he gets half.
Thank you. And they say you are our brother and we divide
it equally.
ספק ובני יבם שבאו לחלוק בנכסי סבא. Safek U-Vnei Yavam Sheba'u Lachlok
Bi-Nichsei Sabba. ספק אמר האי גברא בר מיתנא הוא. Safek Amar Hai
Gavra Bar Mitna Hu. I am ראובן's Reuven son. ופלגא דידי הוא
U-Palga Didi Hu and I get half the field. ובני יבם אמרו
U-Vnei Yavam Amru and the sons of שמעון Shimon say, אחונה, Achuna,
no, you are only our brother. ומנצי לן בהדן U-Mantzi Lan Be-Hadan
and you get a portion with us.
פלגא דקמודי להו שקלי. Palga De-Kamodei Lehu Shakli. Half that he concedes
to them they take. Got it? They are all arguing.
He is claiming that he gets half.
So he concedes that the other half is theirs. I am just
claiming all
of the other half. This half I concede is yours. So this
half they take and they each get a half of the half
so they each get a
quarter so far. Now they're debating this half. He says I get
all of it and they are saying no, we split that three,
we split that.
תילתא דקמודי ליה שקיל. Tilta De-Kamodei Lei Shakil. The third they concede
to him of the remaining half he gets. So he gets a
third of
this
half, which is what?
A sixth. They are debating those two. So we say like
this, פש להו דנקא, Pash Lehu Danka, so you are left with
a sixth. Why a sixth?
Let me see if I got this right.
No, I got it wrong.
Because they actually concede a third of the whole field, excuse me.
Yeah, I was wondering,
right.
They concede, right, they concede a third of the whole field, okay?
They say, right, right. So they say that, right, he says, yeah,
I give, I concede you half. They say, we concede you that
you get a third of the whole field, okay? So I'm not
sure I did this picture correctly, but anyway, you get the idea.
He concedes them a half, they concede a third. So a half
and a third is how much? A half and a third is,
right, so it's 3/6 plus 2/6,
which is 5/6, so what's left is 1/6.
Okay, fine. All right, so, so פשלו דנקא.
Pashlu
danka.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. No, that's right, it's right. Okay, פשלו דנקא, Pashlu
danka, you're left with a sixth of the whole field. הוי ממון
המוטל בספק וחולקין, Havei mamon hamutal besafeik vecholkin, so they divide the
remaining sixth. Okay? Right, yeah. So they get here, between the two
of them, they get a half plus a 12th, which is half
of the
sixth, which is like 7/12.
And he gets a third plus a 12th, which is 5/12. Right.
Okay, so not bad. He gets close to his half.
Okay, not bad. All right, fine.
Okay.
סבא ויבם בנכסי ספק. Sabba veyavam benichsei safeik. Now Yaakov and, now
what, now okay, Gershon dies. Okay, Gershon is the one who dies.
Now Yaakov and Shimon are still alive. They want to get
Gershon's
inheritance. Gershon remember, by the way, got half of Reuven's thing, right?
So Shimon is saying, what's Shimon saying? Shimon is saying, Gershon there
was like my son, right? And I inherit from my son, okay,
everything. Yaakov is saying, he was Reuven's son and if he dies
and Reuven isn't alive, I inherit from him. Okay, so או סבא
וספק בנכסי יבם, O sabba vesafeik benichsei yavam, or the grandfather and
the safeik, now, or Shimon dies. Okay?
And there's no Kehat and Merari, they haven't been born yet. And
Shimon dies. So Gershom is saying he's my dad. Yaakov is saying
he's not your dad, Reuven was your dad and he has nobody
to inherit him and I inherit from him. So in that case,
הוי ממון המוטל בספק וחולקין. Havei mamon hamutal besafeik vecholkin. Each one
comes with a claim, nobody has a stronger claim, you divide it.
All right, that was fun. That was a nice change of pace.
Yes, now we move on. Yeah.
The issue of the, where was, to pass. There was a case
on the West Virginia-Virginia border where a person was missing, they found
the body and they weren't sure, it was body location, they weren't
sure where the border was and they actually had to do a
survey to figure it out.
Okay, so what was the נפקא מינא, Nafka mina, where to bury
him?
Well, any homicide needs to be identified. Oh, it wanted to be
tried in West Virginia because there's no death penalty.
Got it. Okay, moving on. Next, yes.
So all this is only relevant if the person passed away and
didn't leave any documentation because they're allowed to gift.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right, right, this is all, right, correct. All right,
שומרת יבם. Shomeret yavam. Now we get back to יבום Yibbum cases,
but not these crazy things about three brothers and three sisters. Okay.
And a pretty straightforward question about, again, we're in the world of
property and דיני ממונות, Dinei mamonot, about how to understand sort of
where the property rights shift in terms of when the, you know,
in the process of יבום. Yibbum. So let's take a look. שומרת
יבם, Shomeret yavam, a woman waiting for יבום, Yibbum, meaning Reuven died
and Rachel is there waiting for יבום Yibbum or חליצה Chalitzah from
Shimon. So נפלו לה נכסים. Naflo lah nechasim. Now, some relative passed
away and she inherited property while she was in this state.
So what would be the story? So we get to a לשון
Lashon of this. Okay. Reuven
is, he's going to be out of the picture very soon. He
marries Rachel. Okay, there's Shimon. Short lifespan, exactly. And Shimon is waiting,
Rachel is waiting either for him to do יבום Yibbum or חליצה.
Chalitzah. Now she gets property. Now what would be the הלכה Halacha
of property? What's the status of property that a wife owns, that
she has title to? Anybody know? Property that a wife owns is
called,
there are two possibilities.
Right. Well, no, but the standard case that she has title to
is called נכסי מלוג, Nechsei milug, where she has title to it
and the husband gets the פירות. Peirot. Okay, we had that before,
קנין פירות כקנין הגוף. Kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf.
If, remember this is called זיקה Zikah here, so if that made
her like she was married to him, he would get the פירות.
Peirot. If the זיקה Zikah does not make her like she's married
to him, she gets to keep on benefiting from the פירות. Peirot.
Okay, so what is the story that she gets this property while
she's waiting for the יבום? Yibbum? What's the story with that property?
So the משנה Mishnah says. מודים בית שמאי Beis Shammai ובית הלל
*modim Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel*, בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* and
בית הלל Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel* agree שמכרת ונותנת וקיים *shemocheres u'nosnes
v'kayam*. She can buy, she can sell and give the gifts from
the property and it's binding. Not only, by the way, can she
give gifts from the fruit, which was already a חידוש *chiddush* because
the fruit doesn't go to Shimon, but presumably she can even sell
off the property. Okay, and Shimon doesn't have enough of a right.
Remember we had the whole discussion before, קניין פירות peiros, כקניין הגוף
*kinyan peirot k'kinyan haguf*, Shimon does not have enough of a right
to prevent her from gifting that from gifting the property. Okay, so
basically it means in this state Shimon is out of the picture.
Even though he is, there's a זיקה zika *zika* or whatever, she's
totally in control of the property.
Is that צאן ברזל *tzon barzel*?
No, נכסי מלוג nichsei melog, *nichsei milog*. I mean, it's similar, no,
let's not confuse that. Okay, it would have been נכסי מלוג *nichsei
milog* but it's not. If they would be married, Shimon would be
entitled to the fruit, but because they're
not married it's basically just her property free and clear. צאן ברזל
*tzon barzel* is the exact opposite of that. This is basically her
property free and clear.
Now, מתה מה יעשה בכתובתה ובנכסים הנכנסים ויוצאים עמה *meisa ma yaaseh
b'kesuvashah u'v'nichasim hanichnasim v'yotzim imah*. Now she died. Okay, what is the
status? Now she's got a father, Lavan.
Now what is the status with this property? Lavan wants it
all because he says that was my daughter's property, she's died, she
doesn't have any heirs, I get the whole property. I mean she
could have kids also from a different husband, but let's not worry
about that, doesn't matter. Okay, Shimon says no, she was sort of
my wife, and even if I didn't have rights to it while
she was alive, now I should inherit. Of course, that's why do
you get more rights now that she's dead? Okay, so let's see
what the debate is. מה יעשה בכתובתה ובנכסים הנכנסים ויוצאים עמה *ma
yaaseh b'kesuvashah u'v'nichasim hanichnasim v'yotzim imah*. Now this is נכסים הנכנסים ויוצאים
עמה *nichasim hanichnasim v'yotzim imah*, like the property she carries in and
out of the marriage as it were. What's כתובתה *kesuvashah*? כתובתה *kesuvashah*
is Shimon,
the fact
that she's deserved, that to pay out, the fact of what do
you call it when Reuven died,
Reuven owed her her כתובה kesuvah, *kesuvah* of two hundred זוז zuz
*zuz*. All right?
Right? That she should have collected her two hundred זוז zuz, *zuz*
when Reuven died, that's her כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*, right? Yes, that looks
like a big number, two hundred. Okay, except that if she goes
ahead and Shimon takes Reuven's place and marries her, it's not like
a new marriage, it's like a continuation of Reuven's marriage and she
doesn't collect
the כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*. Okay, you got that idea? The כתובה kesuvah,
*kesuvah* isn't really collectable if Shimon were to have done יבום *yibum*.
If Shimon did חליצה *chalitzah* she could collect the כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*.
Otherwise, Shimon is taking Reuven's place. So what happens now that she's
dead? Who gets these properties and who gets the כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*?
All right? So if Lavan's going to collect the כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*,
he's going to collect it from Shimon. Except, parenthetically, I'm sure I'm
confusing you now, he's going to get it out of Reuven's property
that Shimon might have gotten. Anyway, whatever. Okay, so let's move on.
He says like this, so what do you do with that? So
בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו Beis Shammai omrim yachloku, יורש הבעל ויורש האב
*Beis Shammai omerim yachaloku yoresh habaal v'yoresh ha'av*, split it. So it's
not clear is why בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* says that
the husband all of a sudden has more right to this. Okay,
but we'll worry about that. בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* basically
says split it. ובית הלל אומרים *u'Beis Hillel omerim* no, נכסים בחזקתם
*nichasim b'chezkasan*, everything stays with where its status quo had been. So
this is a basic question at the conceptually underlying this question is
do you say ממון המוטל בספק חולקין mamon hamutal besafeik cholekin. *mamon
hamutal b'safek cholkin* or do you say keep it in its חזקה
chazakah. *chazakah*, keep it where it had been. So what had the
status quo been? Says בית הלל Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel*. כתובה kesuvah,
בחזקת יורשי הבעל *kesuvah b'chezkas yorshei habaal*. So the כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*
is uncollected and therefore, yes, she never collected this כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah*,
right? So it's still under the control of the husband's property. Okay,
so he, no, she has no right to
it and where it's still under Shimon's control. She wants to collect
it out of Shimon's property, you want to say she was quasi-married
to Shimon or whatever.
No, that money was totally under Shimon's control. Okay, that seems to
be the בעל *baal* here is Shimon, okay, not Reuven. ונכסים הנכנסים
ויוצאים עמה *v'nichasim hanichnasim v'yotzim imah*, now this property בחזקת יורשי האב
*b'chezkas yorshei ha'av*. Never left her control. She got it, it never
entered under Shimon's control. So it's under the control of her and
her heirs, so that goes to her heirs.
Okay, and so is that clear what בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis
Shammai* and בית הלל *Beis Hillel* are saying? בית הלל *Beis Hillel*
is saying look, she gets this property, this has not been is
not a real marriage yet. So this is under her control, it
stays under her control and it goes to her heirs. The funny
thing is that בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* agrees that while
she's alive it's totally under control. The two hundred זוז zuz. *zuz*,
okay, the כתובה kesuvah *kesuvah* that she stands... collect from let's say
שמעון, Shimon okay,
or ראובן Reuven wherever she so wanted to press her case, that
money hasn't yet been collected. It's still part of ראובן's Reuven estate
or שמעון's Shimon, estate. Since she doesn't have a clear relationship here
with שמעון, Shimon right, that's not that hasn't been like, you know,
consummated or whatever, so that stays under שמעון's Shimon estate. Wait. Why?
Because because if that 200, if it's a continuation of the marriage,
then they were married. If it's not a continuation, if they're not
really married because זיקה zika is not
strong.
Yes, so the basic point is, that's a good point. So what
we're basically notice that בית שמאי Beis Shammai is
saying ממון המוטל בספק חולקין. So what we're really looking at it
is a case of a ספק. safeik. Okay? So the point is
is it so I had stated as weak, I should have stated
as ספק. safeik. You're correct. So let's do it again. So basically,
you know, here, this had been her property. His claim to it
was a doubtful claim, okay, because maybe the זיקה's zika considered like
he's the husband. It was a doubtful claim. But it definitely is
רחל's Rachel and her heirs. The husband is the outsider with a
doubtful claim, so it stays under the control of רחל Rachel and
her heirs. Okay? So you're right. It's more about being ספק safeik
than weak. This רחל's Rachel claim about demanding the 200 זוז zuz?
or whatever, right? She only gets it, you know, when the husband
isn't in the picture as it were. So, right, if the husband
is still in the picture she doesn't get it.
So רחל's Rachel claim is about the fact that שמעון Shimon isn't
in the picture.
Okay? But that property is under שמעון's Shimon control. So he's the
one with the doubtful claim and therefore it stays under שמעון's Shimon
control. So you're right. Thank you. It's all about it being a
ספק. safeik. Okay. So that's בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position... בית הלל's
position that since it's a doubt, it stays under where it began.
Now, the end of the משנה mishna says: כנסה, kinsa, if actually
שמעון Shimon married her, הרי היא כאשתו לכל דבר, harei hi k'ishto
l'chol davar, then it's a full status of wife, which means that
שמעון Shimon now has control over the property. If she dies, שמעון
Shimon will inherit the property. Husband inherits his wife.
Okay. ובלבד שתהא כתובתה על נכסי בעלה הראשון. ubilvad shetehei kesuvahsah al
nichsei baalah harishon. But in that case, when it is time to
collect her כתובה, kesuvah if שמעון Shimon let's say divorces her, she
can't collect it out of שמעון's Shimon, the standard estate of שמעון,
Shimon she has to collect it out of the part of שמעון's
Shimon estate that שמעון Shimon got from ראובן. Reuven. Because it's a
continuation of the כתובה kesuvah that she had against ראובן. Reuven. Is
that clear? Yeah, so since when ראובן Reuven died she was entitled
to this 200 זוז, zuz, but now שמעון Shimon married her and
that was a continuation, so she can't collect her כתובה kesuvah yet.
When שמעון Shimon dies or שמעון Shimon divorces her, she gets her
original כתובה, kesuvah, but it's only based on the estate that שמעון
Shimon took over from ראובן. Reuven. Okay? So if ראובן Reuven had
no property and שמעון Shimon. had property, then ironically she would not
have anywhere to collect her כתובה kesuvah from even though she's been
married to שמעון. Shimon Yes.
Is it also suggesting that financially and practically the יבמה yevamah is
not considered a
widow?
No, widow gets 200 זוז. zuz, Widow or divorcee, either way.
Not 100?
No. Oh, if she oh, oh I see, why isn't it just
100 זוז? Yes, oh good point. I see, you meant the 200
specifically.
Still, she's not considered a
well, right, meaning, that's a good point because this is a continuation
of her כתובה kesuvah against ראובן, Reuven, right,
what Phil is saying is that שמעון Shimon just married a widow,
the כתובה would only be 100 זוז, not 200. But the whole
point, but yeah, but then she would often have a claim directly
against שמעון's Shimon. estate.
That suggests something about the זיקה bond being without an interruption in
marriage. Well, that's what we're exactly saying.
And that's why when she collects her כתובה, she doesn't have really
a כתובה against שמעון. Shimon If שמעון Shimon dies, then the כתובה
she's collecting is against ראובן's Reuven estate that שמעון Shimon. inherited. And
if ראובן Reuven has no estate, then she has no כתובה claims
against שמעון. Shimon, So that's consistent with what the point you made,
which is that if it were a כתובה with שמעון, Shimon, it
would be 100 זוז, but it's not a כתובה with שמעון, Shimon
it's a continuation of the כתובה with ראובן. Reuven. Okay? Yes.
If somebody makes a כתובה, they don't have to put aside that
money? In other words, you're saying he might die without any property.
That's correct.
Poor people are allowed to get married too, you know. So I
mean, but it's
true what's the point of the כתובה what I'm saying is what's
the
point of "I
owe you 200 but I don't have it"?
You might earn it. Who knows? I mean, you know, so by
the time... Okay. All right. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי שנא רישא דלא
פליגי ומאי שנא סיפא דפליגי? Maishana reisha delo paligi umaishana seifa depaligi?
Why when she's alive does בית שמאי Beis Shammai agree that she's
totally in control of this property? And the fact that he has
a doubtful husband status doesn't stop that. But when she dies, then
בית שמאי Beis Shammai goes, "Oh well, he might have been like
the husband and he gets an equal claim to it." So why
when she was alive, why not say he might be the husband
and he gets an equal claim to it? Okay? You got the
question? Reasonable question. מאי שנא רישא דלא פליגי ומאי שנא סיפא דפליגי?
Maishana reisha delo paligi umaishana seifa depaligi? אמר עולא *amar Ulla*, says
עולא *Ulla*, רישא דנפלה כשהיא ארוסה *reisha d'nafla k'shehi arusa*. The first
case is that she fell before שמעון *Shimon* when she had been
an ארוסה *arusa* to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. Okay, I'll spell it out
and then I'll then I'll explain it. וסיפא *v'seifa*, the second case,
דנפלה כשהיא נשואה *d'nafla k'shehi n'sua*, she had been a נשואה *n'sua*
to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. Why does that matter?
Because סבר עולא *savar Ulla* and עולא *Ulla's* assuming זיקת ארוסה עושה
ספק safek, ארוסה *zikas arusa osa safek arusa*. The זיקה *zika* that
derives from the ארוסה *arusa* relationship makes her a doubtful ארוסה *arusa*.
זיקת נשואה עושה ספק safek נשואה *zikas n'sua osa safek n'sua*.
The זיקה *zika* that derived from an נשואה *n'sua* relationship made her
a doubtful נשואה *n'sua*. So, what's the case? He says the difference
is not that רחל Rachel. *Rachel* was alive or dead. Of course,
that's totally what the משנה *mishna* is saying and that's why the
גמרא Gemara *gemara* is going to reject it. Rather than introducing the
difference that is in the משנה *mishna* between the two cases of
whether רחל *Rachel's* alive or dead, it introduces a completely other difference
that's not in the משנה *mishna*. And in the first case where
בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* says she's totally in control, it's
because her relationship to ראובן Reuven *Reuven* had been that of ארוסה
*arusa*. And as a woman is an ארוסה *arusa*, the husband doesn't
yet get rights to the property. The husband only gets rights to
the property when she's a נשואה *n'sua*. So therefore, ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
died, her relationship to שמעון *Shimon* is just as a very beautiful
expression of that, a continuation of her relationship to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*.
So she's a doubtful slash quasi-ארוסה *arusa* to שמעון *Shimon*. Okay, so
she's totally in control of her property. It's only within the ארוסה
*arusa* thing. That's when בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* concedes that
she has total control. When did בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* say that
after she dies, שמעון *Shimon* has a half, you know, gets half
of it? And שמעון *Shimon's* in the picture? That's when she was
a נשואה *n'sua* to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. So then this relationship became
a quasi or doubtful נשואה *n'sua* and that put him in the
picture. Okay? So it has nothing to do with whether she's alive
or dead, it has to do with whether the relationship that transferred
from ראובן Reuven's *Reuven* to שמעון *Shimon* is that of ארוסה *arusa*
or that of נשואה *n'sua*. If it's ארוסה *arusa*, then he has
no claim. If it's נשואה *n'sua*, he's got a doubtful claim, that
might give him half.
Yes, I never realized this before but such clarity, I don't think
if a woman's only an ארוסה *arusa* the מצווה *mitzva* of יבום
*yibum* is still חייב *chayav*?
Yes, we said that way back in the מסכתא *masekhta*, but we
haven't, it's okay, it's been a long time. The גמרא Gemara *gemara*
did have a הוה אמינא *hava amina* otherwise, but we actually did
say it. Okay, yes.
If a husband dies and there are children and the one wife,
does the wife get her כתובה *kesuba* before the children get their
inheritance from the estate?
No, she they
they sort of get the she's like she's like a I mean,
she has like a she has a debt against the estate that
then she collects from the children.
In other words, so she's not her like you know, a company
goes broke whether the stock is preferred or common, you know, so
you know what I mean, the preferred get first. Right. So in
other words, she doesn't get first, her כתובה *kesuba*.
Well, I mean, the point is is that I don't know what
you mean first, she has a claim against the estate and the
heirs take over the estate.
So let let's not go into that any further right now. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like this.
Okay. Now, the גמרא *gemara* says like this. Okay now, זיקת ארוסה
עושה ספק safek ארוסה *zikas arusa osa safek arusa*. Now, why do
we say that the ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, when שמעון *Shimon* inherits the
ארוסה *arusa* status, it's ספק safek ארוסה *safek arusa*? Call her a
definite ארוסה *arusa*, he still has no claim to the property. No,
here's why we're calling it a ספק safek. ארוסה *safek arusa*. זיקת
ארוסה עושה ספק safek. ארוסה *zikas arusa osa safek arusa*, דאי סלקא
דעתך ודאי vaday ארוסה *d'ee salka dachach vadai arusa*, because if it
would be considered like a full ארוסה *arusa* status, then how can
you say מודין בית הלל שמוכרת ונותנת וקיים *modin Beis Hillel she'mocheres
v'noshenes v'kayam* that she can freely sell the property? והתנן V'hatnan, *v'hatnan*,
we teach in a משנה *mishna* later on, נפלו לה נכסים משנתארסה
*naflu lah nechasim m'shenisarsa*, if she has property that she got after
after she became an ארוסה *arusa*, this is not a יבום *yibum*
case, a normal woman became an ארוסה *arusa* then she got property.
בית שמאי אומרים תמכור *Beis Shammai omer timkor*, בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*
says she's totally free to do with that property what she wants,
she's still just an ארוסה *arusa*. ובית הלל אומרים לא תמכור *u'Beis
Hillel omrim lo timkor*, no, לכתחילה *l'chatchila* she can't sell that property
because it's going to be coming into the marriage. So even though
he doesn't yet have rights to her, she shouldn't still sell that
property. אלו ואלו מודים *elu v'elu modin*, שבמכרה ונתנה קיים *she'mochra v'nasna
kayam*
that בדיעבד *b'dieved* it's good. So there בית הלל *Beis Hillel* by
a normal ארוסה *arusa* says only בדיעבד *b'dieved* is the sale good.
Here, it says רחל *Rachel* לכתחילה *l'chatchila* can sell the property. So
why can she לכתחילה *l'chatchila* sell the property? It must be that
the ארוסה *arusa* status that transfers is only a ספק safek *safek*
slash quasi-ארוסה *arusa*. And because it's only this this sort of quasi
or ספק safek *safek* thing, she's entitled even לכתחילה *l'chatchila* to sell
the property. אלא שמע מינה זיקת ארוסה עושה ספק ארוסה *ela sh'ma
mina zikas arusa osa safek arusa*. That's how we know that it
makes a ספק ארוסה *safek arusa*. Now, זיקת נשואה עושה ספק נשואה
*zikas n'sua osa safek n'sua*, now, why do we say that the
זיקה *zika* that transfers from being a נשואה *n'sua* makes her into
a ספק נשואה *safek n'sua*? דאי סלקא דעתך ודאי vaday נשואה *d'ee
salka dachach vadai n'sua*, if it made her like a definite נשואה
*n'sua*, so בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו יורשי הבעל עם יורשי האב *Beis
Shammai omrim yachloku yorshei haba'al im yorshei ha'av*, then why would you
say it's split? If she was ודאי vaday? נשואה *vadai n'sua*, the
husband should get it all. And how could בית הלל *Beis Hillel*
say that the father gets it all? והתנן *v'hatnan* נפלו לה נכסים
*naflu la nechasim* משנישאת *mishenisais*, if she got property after she was
a נשואה *nisua*, אלו ואלו מודים *eilu v'eilu modin*, both, this is
again not a יבום *yibum* case, a normal woman got property, both
בית הלל ובית שמאי *Bais Hillel v'Bais Shammai* agree שמוכרה ונתנה שהבעל
מוציא מיד הלקוחות *shemochra v'nasna shehaba'al motzi miyad halokchos*, so if she
tried to sell the husband can block the sale, okay, that the
husband is totally, now
she has title until she dies but the husband is totally in
control.
So here, so in the case where they say after she dies
they split it because it had been a נשואין *nisuin* relationship which
gave him claim to the property, at least a ספק *safek* claim,
okay, it was a ספק *safek* claim, it wasn't a ודאי vaday
*vaday* claim, right? He doesn't get all the property, he gets half
the property according to בית שמאי *Bais Shammai*. אלא שמע מינה זיקת
נשואה עושה ספק נשואה *ella shma mina zikas nesua osa safek nesua*.
You see it makes it doubtful. So how do we deal with
the fact that according to בית שמאי *Bais Shammai* in case number
one she gets it all, right, case number one she gets it
all, and in case number two when she dies, what happened in
case number two when she dies? שמעון *Shimon* gets half. Okay, why
in case number two is he gets half and in case number
one she gets it all? And the first answer is, case number
one is based on אירוסין eirusin, *eirusin*, okay, it's ארוסה *arusa* and
it's sort of זיקת אירוסין *zikas eirusin* which is like ספק אירוסין
*safek eirusin*, and therefore שמעון *Shimon* is completely out of the picture,
she gets it all. Case number two was when this, when their
relationship had been that of a נשואה *nesua*. So when this is
a זיקת נשואה *zikas nesua*, right, רחל *Rachel* had been a נשואה
*nesua* to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, so when it's a זיקת נשואה *zikas
nesua*, therefore because it's a ספק נשואה *safek nesua*, he gets claim
to a half, okay? If it had been like a ודאי vaday.
נשואה *vaday nesua* he would have claim to the whole thing. All
right, so that's the basic difference. I don't know if that color
confused you or not, but anyway, the basic difference is between the
רישא *reisha* and the סיפא *seifa* is not is she alive or
dead, but was the relationship that transferred one of אירוסין *eirusin* which
gives the שמעון *Shimon* no right, or is it one of נשואין
*nisuin* which gives him questionable or partial rights.
Yeah, but why do we determine these cases at the זיקה *zika*
as ספק *safek*?
No, זיקה *zika* is the relationship that's unconsummated. The הלכה *halacha* consequences
whether זיקת נשואה *zikas nesua* makes her a ספק נשואה *safek nesua*.
So the ספק *safek* is the הלכה *halacha* consequence of that relationship.
The relationship is the word זיקה *zika*.
Okay, but it's because the relationship is a זיקה *zika* relationship. Yes,
that we are that, in other words, it's weaker than the actual.
Correct. Okay.
All right. So הגמרא *hagemara* says like this, so אמר ליה רבא
*amar lei Rava*, רבא *Rava* said one minute,
that's not the difference the משנה'ס *mishna's* making. אטו מפלגי בגופא ולאחר
מיתה *atu mafalgi b'gufa v'le'achar misa*, rather than having the according to
you, rather than having the משנה *mishna* discuss what happens to the
body of the property, you know, who inherits it and after the
death of the woman, so according to you that shouldn't have been
the focus. לפלוג בחייה ולפירות *liflog b'chayeha u'lperos*. It should have just
said what do you do with the fruit while she's alive. And
it should have distinguished between an ארוסה *arusa* and a נשואה *nesua*.
It should have said in the ארוסה *arusa* case she gets to
keep and use the fruit and sell it. In the נשואה *nesua*
case they split the fruit, right? Why did it transfer, why did
the משנה *mishna* shift to a case that she died and we're
trying to make a claim on the property? According to you, it
has nothing to do with her dying. The difference was in one
case she has rights to the fruit because it comes from an
ארוסה *arusa* status, and in the next case she has only partial
or questionable rights because it comes from a נשואה *nesua* status. So
he's pointing at to the simple fact case number two is not
about a difference that's not in the משנה *mishna* about her having
been a נשואה *nesua*. Case number two is about her being dead,
okay? That's what the second part of the משנה *mishna* says. Can't
hard to argue with that logic. אלא אמר רבא *ella amar Rava*,
so rather רבא *Rava* said, אידי ואידי דנפלה כשהיא נשואה *eidi v'eidi
denafla k'shehi nesua*. Both case one and case two is she started
as a נשואה *nesua*. וזיקת נשואה עושה ספק נשואה *v'zikas nesua osa
safek nesua*. And like you said, זיקת נשואה *zikas nesua* is a
ספק *safek* status. So we're back to the question.
So why does, get rid of all these pretty colors, why does
when
she's alive, okay,
why is when she's alive
she's entitled fully to the נכסי מלוג *nechsei milog*, to the נכסים
*nechasim* that fell to her, and why when she's dead is it
the split? So he says well we're going to start with the
fact that this makes her ספק נשואה *safek nesua*. Okay, if it
makes her ספק נשואה *safek nesua* while she's alive he should have
a claim, at least fifty percent of the פירות peiros *peros* while
she's alive, right, because if it was ודאי נשואה *vaday nesua* he'd
get right to all the פירות peiros? *peros*. So why does בית
שמאי *Bais Shammai* concede that case? Let's take a look. He says
like this. רישא דהיא קיימא
*reisha d'hee kayma*, in the beginning when she's alive, הויא לה היא
ודאי ואיהו ספק *havya la hee vaday v'ihu safek*, she's a ודאי
*vaday* and they or whatever he is a ספק *safek*. ואין ספק
מוציא מידי ודאי V'ein safek motzi mi'yedei vaday. *v'ein safek motzi miyedei
vaday*. And she says, "Look buddy, I am a ודאי *vaday*. Okay,
now why am I a ודאי *vaday*? Maybe this is considered
ודאי נשואה *vaday nesua*..." but she is a ודאי in something. Even
by נכסי מלוג, you know what she gets? Even if she doesn't
get the פירות, she has the title, okay. The title belongs to
רחל.
The question
is who gets the fruit? So she says, buddy, I definitely own
the land. You're coming and you say you might be entitled to
the fruit. Okay, get off my property. Okay, so that's what she
says in the first case. So then right. So that is, so
that's in the first case. You're right, it's a ספק, but she's
got the title. Okay, and that's why בית שמאי concede that she
can do whatever she wants. He's got a questionable claim to the
פירות and and he's got a definite ownership of the title. ואין
ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. סיפא דמיתה. Seifa d'meisa. Now, is a second
case she dies. What are they debating now in this case? Are
they debating the פירות? No, they're debating the whole thing, the title.
So he's got a ספק claim, he's got a ספק claim, so
split it. All right.
She's still a ודאי in that case, she's dead.
She's dead, right, she's ודאי dead. Okay. So
סיפא
דמיתה, seifa d'meisa, הללו באים לירשה והללו באים לירשה. halalu ba'im l'irshah
v'halalu ba'im l'irshah. Both are coming to say to to to claim
title. Okay. So and if he was the husband, he would inherit
his wife. If he wasn't the husband, and if it wasn't, you
know, even an אירוסין, he's not entitled to inherit and the father
would inherit. ויחלוקו, V'yachloku, and you divide it. So that's clearly a
nice simple explanation of why בית שמאי concedes when she's alive because
then she have that has a title. The question is when she's
dead and they're debating who owns the title, that's when בית שמאי
says ויחלוקו yachloku and בית הלל says you go by the חזקה.
chazakah, All right, very nice. איתיביה אביי, Eiseivei Abaye, so אביי Abaye
said, ולבית שמאי אין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי? u'l'Beis Shammai ein safek
motzi mi'yedei vaday? One minute. Since when do we say according to
בית שמאי that a ספק claim can't take out of a ודאי?
It's pretty funny because I mean not fully out of a ודאי
but at least to get him get himself fifty percent. והתנן, נפל
הבית עליו ועל אביו עליו ועל מורישיו. nafal habayis alav v'al aviv
alav v'al morishav. A house collapsed on ראובן Reuven and יעקב. Yaakov.
Now, here's a case similar to what you asked me, David. ראובן
has some creditors against him. So what the creditors would like to
say is that
יעקב Yaakov died first, ראובן inherited יעקב, Yaakov, we get a lien
on the property, and then ראובן died. Okay, whereas what the יורשים
yorshim would like to say is ראובן died first and then יעקב
Yaakov and the property never went via ראובן and the creditors have
no claim. Okay, so what do you say? היו עליו כתובת אשה
ובעל חוב, Hayu alav kesuvas isha u'ba'al chov, and you had various
debts against ראובן's property, either a wife's כתובה or other debt. יורשי
האב אומרים, Yorshei ha'av omrim, the heirs say, הבן מת ראשון ואחר
כך מת האב, haben meis rishon v'achar kach meis ha'av, first ראובן
died and then יעקב. Yaakov. ובעלי חוב אומרים, U'ba'alei chov omrim, and
the debtors say, the creditors say, excuse me, האב מת ראשון ואחר
כך מת הבן. ha'av meis rishon v'achar kach meis haben.
יעקב Yaakov died and ראובן inherited it and we have a lien
on the property and then ראובן died. So what do you do?
בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו, you split the property that's being debated, okay,
not all the property but the property that the creditors have a
lien want to claim a lien on because of their debt because
of the outstanding debt, so you split it. It's a ספק. ובית
הלל אומרים נכסים בחזקתם. u'Beis Hillel omrim nechasim b'chezakasam. No, you keep
them in their חזקה, chazakah their חזקה chazakah. basically is under the
control of the יורשים yorshim because the creditors are coming from the
outside, right? This property was definitely under יעקב's Yaakov's control. Creditors are
coming from the outside, so you assume that they have a doubtful
claim.
The creditors have a claim against the son.
Son. So the גמרא says, והכא יורשין ודאי, v'hacha yorshin vaday,
the heirs are definitely in the picture and they have rights to
the property, ובעלי חוב ספק, u'ba'alei chov safek, and the creditors are
a doubt, וקאתי ספק ומוציא מידי ודאי, v'ka'asi safek u'motzi mi'yedei vaday,
and they're coming and they're taking a claim against the field. So
you see that בית שמאי says even in a case of a
definite right to title, somebody coming from the outside could press their
claim even if it's a ספק. So we're back here, when she's
alive, why can't שמעון press his claim? So the גמרא says, no,
that case is special. קסברי בית שמאי, Kasvari Beis Shammai, בית שמאי
holds, שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי, shtar ha'omed ligvos k'gavuy dami, that
since the creditors have an outstanding שטר, shtar, an outstanding writ, okay,
then it's like because that gives liens on the property, that's like
it already is collected. So meaning they also have a חזקה. chazakah
Okay, so when you say who has definite rights, definite חזקה chazakah
to let's say יעקב's Yaakov's field, okay, so what בית שמאי would
say is no, when first of all the heirs don't have a
right to יעקב's Yaakov's field until יעקב Yaakov dies, and when יעקב
Yaakov dies, the creditors have just as much of a standing as
the heirs. This gets back somewhat to your question, David. Normally we
don't say that. Normally you say even if the creditors were right,
right, how would we conceptualize what happened? If the creditors were right,
the heirs inherit, the creditors have a lien, and now they can
come to take the property away from the heirs away from the
heirs, right? And if that's true, they're the ספק and the heirs
are the ודאי. Either way we... up with it, right, and that's
the גמרא's question. The answer is you got it wrong. If the
creditors have an outstanding שטר, shtar, then immediately we award the property
to the creditors. It's not like we give it to the heirs
and then the creditors come and press their claim to take it
away from the heirs. If that were true, they'd be outsiders, אין
ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. ein safek motzi mi'yedei vadai. Why does בית
שמאי here say they have an equal claim? Because if you've got
a שטר, shtar, you come with your שטר shtar to בית דין,
Beis Din, the heirs come, and we split the property. We give
them what they deserve and we give the heirs what they deserve.
And because that's how they conceptualize a normal case, they say in
this case, nobody has a bigger חזקה and you split it. But
in this case, in this case, she's got title, he doesn't have
a שטר, shtar, he just has the right to fruit, so he's
the ספק and he's out of the picture. All right.